Guide to the American Indian Collection 1651-1878 MS 322
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
American Indian Collection
1651-1872
MS 322
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
0.3 Linear feet (1 box)
This collection is composed of various documents relating to the history of American Indians from the early period of European settlement up to the late 19th Century, particularly covering their relationship with European and American settlers, and the colonial and American governments.
Provenance
This is an artifical collection composed of material acquired by the New-York Historical Society at various times.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Scope and Content Note
This collection is composed of an assortment of documents all relating to American Indians. In particular, it concerns their relationship with European and American settlers, as well as the colonial and American governments. Many of the documents concern land disputes and transactions but also cover a number of other topics. It includes correspondence, minutes, speeches, land papers, translations, legal and financial documents and a sketch. Although much of the material relates to the northeast region, it has a broad geographic range, with documents also relating to Indians in Florida, Canada, Georgia and Kansas.
Please note that references to Indian tribes appear as they do in the documents themselves. This relates specifically to the Mohicans, which are described in certain instances as "Maquas" and "Maques".
This collection is described at the item level.
Arrangement
The material is arranged into five series by document type. Each series is arranged chronologically.
Ogden family; Parrish, Jasper, 1767-1836; Canada; Creek War, 1813-1814; Florida; Georgia; Indian reservations -- New York (State); Indians of North America -- History; Indians of North America -- Land tenure; Indians of North America -- Relocation; Indians, Treatment of -- North America; Iroquois Indians; Kansas; New York (State); Society of Friends -- Indians
- Series I: Correspondence, 1702-1878, undated
  Scope and Contents note
  Included in this series is a variety of letters pertaining broadly to relations between American Indians and whites. The earlier material relates largely to relations in New York and New England, with the bulk of the later documents concerning the plight of the Indian tribes, including the Cherokee, in relation to their removal westward.
  More specific topics covered in the letters include: the return of French captives ransomed by New Englanders; discouraging Indians from joining an expedition with the French; Maquas Indian complaints regarding settlement of Indian land; the care of a young Mohawk who contracted smallpox; a petition from the Narragansett regarding land; a letter from chiefs of the Seven Nations to George Washington; pleas for relief efforts and the addressing of grievances; a letter to the Spanish Governor of Pensacola found on a Creek Indian chief killed in the War of 1812; the murder of an Indian in Kansas and a description of Indians in Kansas.
  There are also several letters of sub-agent and interpreter, Jasper Parrish, regarding his work with the Indian tribes of New York, specifically dealing with payment of annuities, potential disposal of reservation land, and data on tribal populations and size of reservations. With these letters is also a contemporary facsimile, apparently of an Indian manuscript discovered in Labrador. It includes a dated note about its provenance on the address leaf.
  Of particular note are letters of introduction for John D. Lang and Samuel Taylor on their trip to visit Indians living west of the Mississippi River in 1842. The letter directed toward Indians themselves is an excellent summary of contemporary white stereotypes of Indian culture and religion.
  - Copy of a letter from the kings, chiefs and leaders of the Chickasaw Nation to the chiefs of the Seneca Nation, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter from "old king" (a Creek Indian) to the Governor of Pensacola, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Statement of the number of Indians belonging to to the Oneida Nation, from Eli Savage to Mssrs. Roice and Morison, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter from New England Justices of the Peace to Colonel Schuyler, 1702 October 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Propositions from the Chiefs of the three tribes of the Maquas to Gov. Hunter, with his reply, 1710 August 22 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter from Philip Livingston and others to [?], 1738 February 4 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter from Hubert Marshall and others to Colonel Stoddard, 1745 December 21 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter from Thomas Scattergood, [J?] Kinsey, and J Smith about a young Mohawk with small pox, 1757 June 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter of introduction for Sinake Chiefs travelling to Sir William Johnson, 1774 June 18 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter from A. Fennis to Adam Comstock regarding Narrangansett peitition, 1793 January 23 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter from the Chiefs of the Seven Nations to the President of the United States, 1796 February 4 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Fragment of a letter referring to an Indian war (possibly Black Hawk's War), 1800s June (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Copy of letter from Jasper Parrish to E. Granger, 1808 October 14 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Copy of letter from Jasper Parrish to Daniel D. Tompkins, 1811 April 20 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Copy of letter from Jasper Parrish to John Armstrong, 1814 July 27 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Copy of letter from Jasper Parrish to S[amuel] A. Ogden, 1819 September 17 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - State of Six Nations population by Jasper Parrish to Thomas L. McKinney, 1824 October 11 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Populations by tribe, acreage, and distance from Canadaiuga by [Jasper Parrish], 1824 October 11 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Circular letter regarding aid for Cherokees to contest their rights in Court, addressed to Clement C. Moore, 1832 January 18 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter of introduction to Indians signed by T[homas] Hartley Crawford and John C. Spencer, 1842 June 21 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter of introduction signed by T[homas] Hartley Crawford and John C. Spencer to Superintendents of Indian Affairs, the agents, sub-agents and other officers, 1842 June 21 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter from [Jonathan?] Ross and Evan Jones to Rev. Dr. Brainerd, 1864 February 15 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Copy of a letter from Isaac T. Gibson to Vincent Colyer, 1871 January 28 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter from John B. Jones to John D. Lang, 1871 September 26 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter from Felix R. Brunot to John D. Lang, 1872 December 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Copy of a letter from James Obadiah to J.M. Bryan, endorsed by Bryan, 1877 October 1 - 1878 April 30 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter from "William" to his mother, 1878 April 29 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter from J.M. Bryan to William Stickney, endorsed by [Wm?]Stickney to John D. Lang, 1878 April 30 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II: Legal and Financial Documents, 1651-1787
  This series contains various legal and financial documents relating to negotiations and sales of land with Indians. Geographically, the documents include New York and its vicinity, as well as Canada and Georgia. The first folder of the series is composed of a conveyance, order for payment, receipt, deed, mortgage, boundary agreement, two lists of expenses and disbursements, and a fragment of a deed.
  The remaining material is a small collection of papers relating to the interests of speculators who purchased pre-emptive rights to Indian Reservation land in New York, through the Ogden Land Company. The rights involved property on the Buffalo Creek, Cannadea, Cattaraugus, Tonnewanda, Tuscarora and Seneca reservations. The documents specifically relate to the share held by the Murray family, including John R. Murray, Mary Murray, Hannah Murray and Susan Ogden.
  The papers are composed of various types of documents; among them are accounts, a plan of division, a list of lots, a report of a meeting of proprietors, an agreement of exchange of lots, a certificate of redemption of land, and estimates. Additionally, there are copies of documents concerning the disputed Treaty of 1838 between the United States government and Indian tribes of New York. Many of the items contain information concerning property, including taxes, township location, lot number and acreage.
  - Copy of an affadavit concerning the sale of land of the west shore of the North River to Andries de Voss and Arent Andriessen, by Naenkopquieck and Naenemari, 1651 April 29 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Agreement concerning the bounds of West Hook, 1703 October 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Conveyance of property in Georgia from Malatchi Opiya Mico to Thomas and Mary Bosworth, 1747 January 4 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Fragment of a deed from New York Indians to John Christopher Hartwick, 1756 July 15 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bill of Louis Van Vechten for expenses in treating with Indians of German Flatts, 1775 September 11 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Pay and Disbursements in the Indian Department, 1777 March 25 - September 24 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Order on the State Treasurer to pay William Van Ingen, 1785 November 10 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Receipt by Joseph Hamilton for negotiation of land purchase from Western Indians, 1787 May 29 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - New York Indian Reservation Papers, 1817-1848 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series III: Draft, Notes, Minutes, and Speeches, circa 1689-1859, undated
  Within this series are a variety of documents relating to New York State Indians, including those moved west following the Treaty of 1838. The items comprise a draft, speeches, a set of notes, and reports and abstracts of minutes of Yearly Meetings of Friends.
  The documents cover diverse topics such as 1689 hostilities with Maques Indians; assistance and refuge for Oneida Indians during the American Revolution; the removal of whites in violation of a treaty by residing in the Cannajohary-Fort Hunter region; suggestions to Seneca chiefs on the Cattaraugus Reservation on managing and improving land, proper conduct of a family and an exhortation against the use of alcohol; and a request for compensation for Indians displaced under the Treaty of 1838.
  Other material relates to the Society of Friends' efforts on behalf of Indian tribes moved west of the Mississippi. Included in this are a printed report from the Committee on Indian Concern at the 1839 Yearly Meeting with a handwritten abstract of minutes of Yearly Meetings, 1837-1841, and finally a document regarding the decision of John D. Lang and Samuel Taylor to visit those Indian tribes residing west of the Mississippi, 1842.
  - Address to the Chiefs of the Seneca Nation and others residing in Cattaraugus Reservation, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Notes on hostilities with Maques Indians, circa 1689 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - A Speech of the Oneida Chiefs to Lieutenant Colonel Van Dyck, 1780 June 18 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Copy of a petition by Mohawks to the Legislature of the State of New York, 1788 January 12 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Abstract of the Yearly Meeting of Friends for New-England, relative to the Indians residing West of the Mississippi, 1837-1841 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Manuscript copy of "Korte Antwerp van de Mahakuase Indianen, in Nieuw Mederlandt, haer landt, Stature, Diacht, Manieren, en Magistraten; beschreven in 't jaer 1644 Door Johannen Megapolensen, Juniorem Predikant aldaer" (printed in N-YHS Collections 1857, 2nd series, volume 3, page 137), circa 1843 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - A Report from the Committee on Indian Concern, 1839 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Certificate of New-England Yearly Meeting regarding the resolution of John D. Lang and Samuel Taylor to visit Tribes of Indians residing west of the Mississippi, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Incomplete draft of request for compensation to Indians displaced under Treaty of 1838, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series IV: Translations, 1684-1869
  The earliest material is a later, true copy of a translation entitled "The Indian Interpreter" extracted from the "Book of Town records of the Salem Colony"(NJ), with a newspaper and associated documents. The series also includes an undated collection of documents relating to Indian translations of prayers and psalms.
  - Excerpt from "The Indian Interpreter", 1684, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Indian translations of prayers and psalms, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series V: Sketch
  This sketch notes that it depicts Black Hawk, with an accompanying note attributing it to "Dr. DeCamp". This may be Dr. William H. DeCamp of Grand Rapids Michigan who served as a surgeon in the 1st Michigan Engineers and Mechanics during the Civil War. He also participated in the excavation of Indian mounds in Michigan. Its style and focus on Black Hawk's facial features suggest an ethnological influence.
  - Sketch of Blackhawk, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)